Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002 RL.00605
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International Monitor Institute. Burma Videotapes
circa 1990-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International Monitor Institute
RL.00605
12 Linear Feet
The non-profit agency International Monitor Institute (IMI) operated between 1993 and 2003, primarily to assist international war-crimes tribunals by collecting, indexing and organizing visual evidence of violations of international human rights law. The International Monitor Institute Records, Burma Videotapes span the dates 1992-2002, and comprise audiovisual materials related to IMI's documentation of contemporary conflicts and human rights violations in Burma (Myanmar). These audiovisual records largely document the activities, interviews, speeches, press conferences and ceremonies of political figures, especially Aung San Suu Kyi, and document the activities of political and military institutions such figures represent, including the All Burma Students Democratic Front (ABSDF), the National League for Democracy (NLD) and the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC). Records also include extensive network and independent story packages of Burma and footage of human rights conflicts. Topics and footage cover life in Burma under military regime, refugees and refugee camps (especially Karen refugees), political prisoners, survivor stories, forced labor, Japan's role in the refugee situation, and Los Angeles protests against the SLORC and Unocal. These records include copies of approximately 268 video cassettes. The video and audio material is indexed by an extensive database developed by IMI which includes keywords, air dates, segment producer, and segment title. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive. Further organizational material on Burma can be found in the International Monitor Institute Records, also at the Rubenstein Library.
287 Items
Access Restrictions
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center.The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The International Monitor Institute. Burma Videotapes were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006-2007.
Biographical Note for Pippa Scott
The International Monitor Institute (IMI) was founded in 1993 by actress and film producer Pippa Scott. Scott, daughter of screenwriter Allan Scott who wrote some of the Astaire-Rogers films, was educated in California and in England, at Radcliffe College and the Southern California Institute of Architecture. Ms. Scott acted in such films as "The Searchers" and "Auntie Mame," and was a founding partner of the Emmy-award winning television company Lorimar Productions (producer of such TV hits as "The Waltons" and "Dallas" ). Scott established Linden Productions in 1987 to develop documentaries focusing on current issues. Linden's latest production is "King Leopold's Ghost," a documentary about the exploitation of the Congo by King Leopold II of Belgium. Scott was a member of the Women's Refugee Commission, the Pacific Council on Foreign Relations, and the Los Angeles World Affairs Council.
Historical Note for the International Monitor Institute
Organizational History. The International Monitor Institute was founded in 1993 and operated until 2003. Its primary mission was to assist international war-crimes tribunals by collecting, indexing and organizing visual evidence of violations of international human rights law. Videos and audio tapes were acquired through donation as well as on collecting trips by IMI associates in the former Yugoslavia, Kuwait, Rwanda, Sierra Leone, Iraq, Burma (Myanmar), Thailand, Cambodia, and other countries. IMI's activities also included developing regional archives of videos on conflict and human rights abuses, producing film and multimedia projects to assist humanitarian organizations, organizing public outreach events, conducting video research for governments, film makers, authors, and students, and providing educational outreach. Patrons and partners of IMI and its collections included the International Criminal Court and its staff, Human Rights Watch, Physicians for Human Rights, the Simon Wiesenthal Center, the governments of Bosnia-Herzegovina and Croatia, and former First Lady Hillary Clinton.
Collection Overview
The Burma Videotapes section of the International Monitoring Institute records contains descriptions of 286 tapes collected by IMI that depict human rights issues and themes in Burma. Material includes amateur footage, news coverage, commercial productions, as well as material from independent production companies. The format of materials include network documentaries; first-hand footage; interviews with both political figures and unidentified Burmese, particularly Burmese survivors, migrant workers, and refugees; recordings of award ceremonies and speeches; news coverage of street protests in Burma as well as protests in Los Angeles, especially those of the Burma Forum LA. Topics range from military activities and movements; the refugee situation and refugee camps; forced and migrant labor; minefield survivors; the political activities of the National League for Democracy (NLD), the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC), the All Burmese Student Army and other prominent organizations, including other student organization, operating in Burma; everday life under the military regime; the Japanese role in the refugee situation; the problem of widespread rape; rescued girls and children; methods of torture; testimony of massacres and other abuses; as well as documentation of Burmese cultural events, including tribal dances and Burmese song. The majority of videotapes are in NTSC VHS format. Other formats include PAL Betacam SP, NTSC Betacam SP and PAL VHS. Please note that the descriptions of the tapes in this collection are based on IMI's data and were not originally drafted by Rubenstein Library Staff. Tape numbers BU092-BU119 were not transferred to the Rubenstein Library and descriptions of these tapes have been omitted from this finding aid. Further organizational material on Burma can be found in the International Monitor Institute Records, also at the Rubenstein Library.
Collection Arrangement
Tapes are arranged in numerical order by Tape ID, a unique identifier assigned by IMI at the time they cataloged the tapes.
Related Material
International Monitor Institute records. Rwanda videotapes and audiotapes, 1992-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
International Monitor Institute Records,1986-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
HU OSA 350, Fonds 350: Records of the International Monitor Institute
Open Society Archives, Central European University
Burmese students -- Foreign countries; Forced Labor -- Burma; Documentaries (motion picture genre); Human Rights -- Burma; Massacres -- Burma; Military government -- Burma; Rape -- Burma; Burma -- Relations -- Japan; Refugee camps -- Burma; Burma -- Social life and customs; Torture -- Burma; National League for Democracy (Burma); Karen National Union; International Labour Organizaton; Unocal Corporation; Tin Oo, U; State Law and Order Restoration Council (Burma); Ne Vaṅʻʺ, Ūʺ, 1911-2002; Aung San Suu Kyi; ASEAN
- Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002, 287 videocassettes
  Conditions Governing Access note
  RESTRICTED: Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies.
  - Burma Diary, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:55:00] (2 copies) (Box 291, Video-cassette BU001)
    Scope and Contents note
    Produced by: Bay Area Video Coalition.
    Diary: Edited Report by Jeanne Hallacy for Bay Area Video Coalition (English).
    This video portrays a general picture of Burma's struggle for democracy and the Junta's human right abuses, and includes interviews with refugees, deserters and soldiers from the student army and an exiled student named Htin Aung.
    Behind the peaceful landscape and holiness of the pagodas, we see evidence of the torture of Burmese people. The people's demand for democratic changes in 1988 resulted in thousands of deaths.Thousands of students fled Burma in order to plan a coup against the regime.
    In 1992 reporters visited Manawplaw HQ of Karen National Union on the Thai border. The student army, All Burma Students' Democratic Front (ABSDF), joined them.
    Htin Aung was from a family of 10. His brothers and sisters were scattered and jailed.He could not attend the funerals of either of his parents.
    Htin Aung fled Burma with his family and left his little sister behind with villagers and never saw her again.
    Chatate's parents were killed by the army. He ran away and ended up joining ABSDF. He said, "I am not scared. I am holding a gun not a stick...."
    Kevin, an American living in Manawplaw said, "Nonviolent? After your father was taken as porter and your mother was raped and you were forced to watch? What can you expect?"
    In 1994 Htin Aung married San San Aye and had twin daughters. "As long as Burma is not free," he said, "we won't go back.We will stay here. We will fight if not in our generation then my daughters will carry on."
    An interview was conducted with two deserters from the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) who talked about abuses to porters.
    In January 1995 Manawplaw fell. Htin Aung was in the jungle at the time and his two daughters were hit by malaria.
    A reporter in Rangoon met San's parents with Aung San Suu Kyi.
    The National League for Democracy's (NLD) stand on ABSDF is as follows: "Unfortunately we can't stop them from taking up arms because we can't guarantee their safety here."
    During Christmas 1995, Htin Aungwas in Bangkok. In 1996, he left for Australia where he stayed in the Refugee Processing Camp for a year.
    At the end of the interview with one student and Myint Myint San about torture in prison, Htin Aung said: "My country will win finally." The reporter remarked, "The picture records the moment of truth before they are changed."
  - BBC: 40 Million Hostages, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:46:00] (2 copies) (Box 291, Video-cassette BU002)
    Produced by: BBC
    Network: BBC
    Report on the struggle for Democracy in Burma and the army's treatment of the Burmese people. Includes footage from various demonstrations that occurred in 1988 and footage of the Burmese army firing on demonstrators; amateur footage of injured or dead protesters being carried away by other protesters; and scenes from the All Burma Student Democratic Front (ABSDF) training camp.
    Various interviews with Burmese refugees who have escaped to Thailand and who give accounts of torture, detainment, forced labor, forced portage and arbitrary killings. Documentary also features interviews with Aung San Suu Kyi, Ohn Gyaw (Foreign Affairs Ministry), and Karen refugees.
    Report on the National League for Democracy led by Aung San Suu Kyi and how she came out as the single strongest party to challenge the regime sponsored National Unity party. The National League for Democracy (NLD) won 81% of the total seats in parliament. Ne Win's government arrested and/or intimidated many parliament members and encouraged them to abandon their support for the NLD. Ne Win's government announced an open door trade policy. Thailand, Japan, United Kingdom and USA are trading with Burma and China has supplied arms.
    Burmese refugees who have escaped to Thailand: Unidentified male 2: "When we arrived at the monastery and looked back we saw some young women cowering; they fell into the gutter. The government thugs bayoneted these young women and beat them up with batons."; Unidentified female 1: "The soldier ordered my brother to dig his own grave.Then they cut off his arms and then his legs. Then they cut out his tongue and gouged out his eyes. Then they pushed him into the grave and shot him twice through the head and then filled in the pit."; Unidentified male 7: "I was not fed. They asked me if I wanted to eat. I said I did, so they said, 'Here's some food' and they stood on my face until blood came out of my ears.The sergeant asked me if I realized who he was, and I said I didn't. Then they tied me up to a tree and left me there for seven days."
    Ohn Gyaw (Foreign Affairs Ministry): "The demonstrators, there were about twenty. But five-hundred-and-twenty-five looters. Of course there are many people on the streets. The shooting scene was only one scene. You can check again, whatever tapes only one scene of the army is shooting in the crowds, thousands would have been killed."
  - Asia Works: Three interviews with Aung San Suu Kyi (August '97 and November '96), PAL Betacam SP [TRT 00:40:00] (2 copies) (Box 291, Video-cassette BU003)
    Produced by: Images Aisa
    Interview Episode 1:
    In August 1997, Aung San Suu Kyi discussed various economic and political issues taking place in Burma and the National League for Democracy (NLD): "Investment in Burma won't be a success due to instability and inflation. Dialogue is the best possible solution to the problems in Burma." She expressed the NLD's readiness for comprehensive dialogue with the government, not merely a meeting. Although Suu Kyi's movements were restricted and her speeches were not reaching the public,people could get the updates through Radio Free Asia, BBC, VOA or theDemocratic Voice of Burma. Regarding the political stalemate, Suu Kyi said, "Politics is not a drama, it is everyone's life.The regime-sponsored National convention will not bring genuine democracy because their members do not truly represent the people." When generals accused her of being a dictator in NLD, she said generals did not understand democracy.
    Interview Episode 2.
    November 1996: Burmese citizens do not have the right to file a complaint when they are deprived of political rights by the government. Although the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) signed the United Nations Convention on Child Abuse,they did not prevent children from working in government projects. SLORC must deliver basic family rights before it can go further.(Continue interview in Tape 4)
  - Asia Works: Interview with National League for Democracy (NLD) leaders & Aung San Suu Kyi, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:31:00] (2 copies) (Box 291 and 298, Video-cassette BU004)
    Produced by: Images Asia
    Network: Asia works
    Continuation from tape 3.
    NLD leaders appear outdoors, after Aung San Suu Kyi's three cars are attacked by the Union Solidarity Development Association (USDA).
    An underage worker working on a road project in Rangoon, patching the potholes with the melted bitumen by hands.
    "If one is forced to workagainsthis will, it is forced labor no matter how noble the project may be. Labor culture thrives in Burma."
    In June 1996, 4 points people's desire was very paranoid. The State Law and Order Restoration Council Council (SLORC)-sponsored anti NLD marches were not evidence of NLD's failure. People are forced to attend those rallies. General Kyaw Ba was mentioned threatening Suu Kyi on the dialogue issues. When Lee Kuan Yew commented that SLORC should be in power to prevent what had happened in Bosnia from happening in Burma, Suu Kyi said Bosnia's problem was not caused by a weak government but rather by a strong government's prolonged oppression.
    In November 1996, a riot scene from Rangoon right after Suu Kyi's car was attacked by around 200 members of the Union Solidarity Development Association (USDA); SLORC sponsored the youth wing members. Suu Kyi and the other executive committee members were seen persuading people not to retaliate but to go home safely.
  - Asia Works: Interview with Aung San Suu Kyi, November 1996, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:31:00] (3 copies) (Box 298, Video-cassette BU005)
    Network: Asia Works
    November 1996
    Suu Kyi's brief appearance in public.
    Interview with Aung San Suu Kyi on the international economic sanction on Burmese Military Government.
    The State Law and Order Restoration Council's (SLORC) open market economy does not benefit the majority. It only benefits the elite.The system is not a genuine market economy but "crony capitalism." The sanctions will not benefit the vast majority who are not also beneficiaries of market economy. The SLORC does not spend on public health, education and other development programs at all. Sanctions will force the bankrupt SLORC to the dialogue table with the National League for Democracy (NLD). The timing of this will be when there is a confirmed repression being committed by the SLORC against citizens and an opposition such as the mass arrest of NLD members and a physical attack on NLD members by the Union Solidarity and Development Association (USDA). Suu Kyi expressed that NLD's will is free, free from harassment and arrests of the members.
    Suu Kyiappeared in the public with NLD CEOs.
  - AsiaWorks: Press conference inside the temporary Congress Hall prior to aborted National League for Democracy (NLD) National Congress (1996), Part I, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:31:00] (Box 298, Video-cassette BU006)
    Produced by: AsiaWorks
    Brief Scene of Aung San Suu Kyi's compound and the NLD Headquarters.
    Interview with Aung San Suu Kyi, October 2,1996.
    Press conference: May 1996, Suu Kyi announced that 195 elected representatives, 10 ordinary members and 12 from the youth wings were arrested so far by the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) in an attempt to obstruct the NLD congress. All ECs are still free. NLD intends to go ahead as planned. SLORC claimed that NLD did not enjoy popular support. Suu Kyi countered that SLORC spent a great deal ofenergy to arrest and disrupt NLD congress which is much smaller than a SLORC wedding; proof that SLORC is nervous. Sanctions won't hurt great the majority of Burmese. Investments benefit only a small fraction of population closed to SLORC who are already wealthy. Suu Kyi joked about taking military intelligence's (MI) pictures and publishing them.
    Press Conference: NLD is always ready for dialogue. NLD will lead Burma toward democracy as soon as possible. Suu Kyi claimed that 1996 was the critical year for Burma's democracy. Investments can't be stopped but no profit is expected. In Burma there is no rule of law and the economy is in bad shape. It was not known how much the Japanese government had provided in humanitarian aid to Burma. Arrests and harassments have proven that SLORC is nervous about NLD. Suu Kyi was released but not free. SLORC would be happy if she leaves Burma. More arrests including Suu Kyi's arrest was anticipated. SLROC has broken promises.
    Suu Kyi walked while newsmen followed. She mentioned U Win Htein's arrest and the emotional matter.
    Interviews after the Congress were canceled due to road blocks in October 1996. Suu Kyi announced that a total of over 500 were detained. All those efforts were wasted due to lack of dialogue. When asked if the Burmese see no hope and no sign of change, she said people had no choice except to hope and wait and work. But people will never give up on peace and justice. She never breaks promises. SLORC gives out false information on her and NLD. SLORC does not allow her to go on out of town trips. SLORC persuades Asian diplomats not to invite her.Phone calls are intercepted. Her security is SLORC's excuse but is actually more for digging information. (Continued on tape 7)
  - ABC: Report on Burma, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:10:00] (Box 298, Video-cassette BU006)
    Produced by: ABCSpanish edition
    Spanish version of ABC News on Burma:
    Aung San Suu Kyi's speech on heroin victims in Burma.
    Report on C-Span on HR 3540, the Foreign Operation Appropriation Act.
  - Images Asia: Interview with Aung San Suu Kyi, October 2, 1996; Part II, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:31:04] (Box 298, Video-cassette BU007)
    Produced by: Image Asia/AsiaWorks
    Interview Continued from Tape 6
    Two people interviewed by ABC, U Win Htein & Eva (Maung San Hlaing) were arrested as part of the State Law and Order Restoration Council's (SLORC) intimidation campaign. Suu Kyi and some National League for Democracy (NLD) members will continue to work. They know the consequences of doing so. NLD as a political party has to function as it is supposed to.
    Chicago Herald Tribune's Burmese article was cut out with scissors. U Aye Win, Suu Kyi's assistant, was nowhere to be found. Some members were released. Final statistics showed over 800 were arrested nationwide. Only 20 to 30 had been charged and only 23 released. Suu Kyi said, "Too much blood has been spilled, that many have been put into jail. People have tried. What more could we do? Bloodshed before change is a wrong concept. We don't believe in violence." End Interview.
    Su Kyi's home: The Junction was filled with soldiers driving away and arresting supporters who go to her home, September 29 & 30 1996.
    Interview on September 30 1996:SLORC released Suu Kyi. "Dialogue is the ultimate tool to solve problems in Burma. Dialogue is not a boxing match in which one will beat up the other to win. If conditions and the environment change toward an acceptable level, NLD will join the convention."
    NLD is being marginalized due to the convention. The economy has never been good enough. 40% to 90% of the farmers are starving due to the government's export-oriented policy which forces farmers to sell crops with the government prices. Investment is never good for the public but good to the few close to SLORC. NLD has no intention to strip those who are rich due to SLORC's policy. NLD won't lead the country back to 1988. We will lead the country ahead.
  - Nobel Peace Prize Award Ceremony 1991, NTSC VHS [TRT 2:15:00] (Box 298, Video-cassette BU007)
    Produced by: Nobel Committee
    Forty Million Hostages (see Tape 2 )
    Nobel Peace Prize 1991, Award Ceremony for Daw Aung San Suu Kyi
    Oslo, Norway. (English: 1: 10Hrs)
    Dispatches. Edited reportby Christopher Mould, "Burma Dying for Democracy," Channel 4, Great Britain. Screen venture production 1989. ( English43 Minutes)
    7.070
    Noble Peace Prize award ceremony,1991. Dignitaries arrive on red carpet. Michael Aris, husband of Aung San Suu Kyi and their two sons, Alexander & Kim, enter the hall and the Nobel Committee follows. The other laureates follow. Portrait of Aung San Suu Kyi hangs over the wall. Family take their seats. Big crowd gathered outside. King of Norway arrives. Symphony plays an Andante. Opening remarks of the Nobel committee.
    Musical number to honor Aung San Suu Kyi byduo, with Burmese Soung, Mya Man Giri Thein Tan.
    Gold medal & diploma received by husband Michael Aris and Alexander & Kim Aris, sons of Aung San Suu Kyi.
    Alexander spoke for Aung San Suu Kyi. Received on be half all who sacrificed in pursuit of the democratic Burma. Today coincided with Human Rights Day.
    Orchestra plays. Freedom march allegro, Dignitaries shake, then family leaves the hall and ceremony concludes.
    Burma dying for democracy: Students chant: "Burma our land. This is our time to go out and fight for freedom."